Guide to the Rabbi Jimmy Kessler Collection, 1943-2019 MS 887
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rabbi Jimmy Kessler Collection
1943-2019
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kessler, Jimmy, Rabbi
MS 887
1 Linear Feet 2 box
This collection is made up of two boxes containing correspondence, media, event materials, directories, and memorabilia that document part of Rabbi Jimmy Kessler's life from 1943 to 2019.
Biographical / Historical
Rabbi Kessler was born in Houston, Texas, December 10, 1945. After attending local schools including being valedictorian and president of his graduating class at San Jacinto Senior High School, he earned his BA from the University of Texas in Austin, where he was a member of Tau Delta Phi fraternity. He earned the first doctorate in Texas Jewish history, at the Hebrew Union College Jewish Institute of Religion in Cincinnati, where he was also ordained as a rabbi.
Rabbi Kessler first served as director of the Texas Hillel, which serves the students attending the University of Texas. While there, Kessler taught very popular courses in the Religious Studies programs at UT and served on several committees at the request of the University president. He was a counselor at a summer retreat for Jewish youth - Echo Hill Ranch. Based on his long interest in Texas Jewish history, Kessler founded the Texas Jewish Historical Society in 1980. In July 2009, Kessler became the first rabbi in the 171-year history of Texas freemasonry to be named the presiding officer of a Masonic lodge, when Harmony Lodge of Galveston installed him as its new leader. Harmony Lodge was established in 1839.
Exerpted from: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Kessler
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of two boxes containing correspondence, media, event materials, directories, and memorabilia that document part of Rabbi Jimmy Kessler's life from 1943 to 2019.
This collection forms part of the South Texas Jewish Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Rabbi Jimmy Kessler donated materials in July 2019; Shelley Kessler donated materials in March 2023.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in four series as follows:
Series I: General; Series II: Media; Series III: Memorabilia; Series IV: Addenda
Related Materials
Although not accessioned with this donation, Rabbi Kessler previously donated a signed copy of his book: Henry Cohen - The Life of a Frontier Rabbi. The book is cataloged (BM755.C6 K47 1997) and is available at the Woodson Research Center.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
Video recordings; Collectibles
- Series I: General
  - A Tour of Jewish Galveston Coloring Book, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Happy Birthday Note from Rabbi Kessler, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Media
  - Henry Cohen: The Life of a Frontier Rabbi DVD, n.d. (Box 1)
  - "A Conversation with Dr. Jacob Radar Marcus, Rabbi and Historian" DVD (Box 1)
- Series III: Memorabilia
  - Ration Stamps, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ration Books Bag, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Texas Jewish Historical Society Keychains, 1980; 1993 (Box 1, Envelope 5)
  - Echo Hill Ranch 40th Anniversary Keychain, 1993 (Box 1, Envelope 6)
  - Echo Hill Ranch 40th Anniversary Pins, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kinky Friedman for Governor Pin, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Texas Hillel Topfer Center Dedication Ceramic Bag, 2006-02-05 (Box 1, Box 9)
  - Shep Fields' Rippling Rhythm Orchestra Lighter from Shamrock Hilton Hotel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kinky Friedman Cigar, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Little Jewford Kazoo, n.d. (Box 1, Envelope 12)
- Series IV: Addenda
  - Jimmy Kessler's Bar Mitvah book, 1959-01-02-1959-01-03 (Box 2)
  - El Oroso, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Memorial Obituary Bookmark for Dr. Harry Samuel Kessler, 1965-08-01 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Group photo, Ordination Class HUC-JIR, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, the first meeting of the Texas Jewish Historical Society, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - San Jacinto High School Alumni Directories (2), 2012; 2022 (Box 2)
  - Program, Congregation K'nesseth Israel 90th Anniversary and Hurricane Harvey Restoration Service & Celebration, 2019-04-07 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Galveston Jewish Burials, CD, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Henry Cohen: The Life of a Frontier Rabbi and Temple B'nai Israel: The History of a BOI, DVD (Box 2)
  - 43rd Street Cemetery, CD, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Program, Memories are made of this..., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)